In this video, we will be going slightly
more
advanced and we will be talking about
normal
forces and gravity.
So, first of all, I'll explain as we go.
A 6kg box rests on a smooth, inclined
plane
that makes an angle of 35 degrees with a
horizontal.
Normally, as we've learned before, the
normal
force is usually directly opposite to the
gravity
force. For example, if we have a box on a
surface,
there will be a gravity force here and
there
will be a normal force pointing exactly in
the
opposite direction over here.
However, on an inclined plane, things get
a
little different. Let's say we have an
inclined
plane of 35 degrees here. And we have a
box,
let's draw it a bit down, over here.
Force of gravity is always pointed
straight
down. It's pointed towards the centre of
the
Earth, so it would be pointed somewhere
towards
here. However, the normal force is the
force
that the surface exerts on the box.
So, the surface, if it's going here, the
normal
force should be perpendicular to the
surface.
In fact, the normal force is always
perpendicular
to the surface because the surface is the
one
that's exerting the force. So, the normal
force
would look something like this. F-N and
F-G.
That are all the forces that there are on
this
box. You might be thinking that there will
be
a force that makes the box go, and you
might
call it F-A, but that force is actually a
component
of the gravity force. Gravity is the thing
that
makes the component slide, so don't draw
something
like this. That's just a component of
gravity.
And basically, these are the only two
forces,
if we don't take into account for the
friction.
Yeah, the direction is perpendicular to
the
surface. Determine the angle of the normal
force
makes with the vertical. Well, the
vertical
is like this, and if the vertical is
perpendicular to the horizontal, and the
incline
is 35 degrees to the horizontal, and the
normal
force is perpendicular to the incline,
then
do you agree that this will be 35 degrees?
It will. So, that will be the angle the
normal
force makes with the vertical, 35 degrees.
Now calculate the magnitude of normal
force
acting on the box. And now what we do is
we
can bring this to a more zoomed in view.
We have the normal force over here, let's
call
this F-N, and we have the gravity pointing
straight
down over here, let's call this F-G.
So now, what we can do is we can actually
translate
this force, this normal force, down over
here.
So we actually bring it down over here.
Since
it's a vector, we can do that. And the
reason
why we do that is since F-G is perfectly
in
the same direction as the vertical, it is
literally
the vertical, and we know that F-N makes
an
angle of 35 degrees to the vertical, we
know
that this is 35 degrees, and this is F-N.
And now we can calculate a lot of things,
because
we know that this is a right angle,
we can make it a right angle. And yeah,
now
F-N is just force of gravity, which is a
hypotenuse,
times cosine of 35 degrees, because cosine
is
adjacent over hypotenuse. What is F-G?
Well, F-G is equal to mass times
acceleration.
We learned that in a previous lesson, all
the
way up here. F equals M-A, cosine 35.
Well, what is our mass? We have that
given,
6.0. Acceleration is just the acceleration
of
gravity, which is 9.81.
Cosine of 35 would be
around 0.819.
And when you multiply that all together,
you
get around 48 newtons to sig figs, because
of
this. And that would be your magnitude for
the
normal force. And basically, as a rule of
thumb
for the future, if you have a problem with
a
smooth incline plane, you don't need to
draw
this out unless you need to show your
work.
If it's multiple choice, just remember
that
the normal force is the force of gravity
times
cosine of that incline angle.
And this is how we derive that. It's easy
to
derive as well if you want to know how to
do
it. 48 newtons.
Okay, does the normal force depend on the
mass
of the box, the angle of incline, or both?
Well, that's really, really easy.
We can see our formula. The normal force
is
mass times acceleration times cosine of
the
angle of incline. So, normal force
actually
depends on both. If one of these variable
changes,
the normal force changes. So, this would
be
both. And that's it for a video of normal
force.
Remember, normal force is the force that
counteracts
gravity, but it is always perpendicular to
the
surface on which the object is on. Thank
you
for listening.